<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>bylr.info</title>
    <link>https://bylr.info/</link>
    <description>Recent content on bylr.info</description>
    <image>
      <url>https://bylr.info/android-chrome-512x512.png</url>
      <link>https://bylr.info/android-chrome-512x512.png</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2022 Antoine Beyeler –</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://bylr.info/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Annotated Release Notes: vpype 1.10</title>
      <link>https://bylr.info/articles/2022/04/07/annotated-release-notes-vpype-1.10/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bylr.info/articles/2022/04/07/annotated-release-notes-vpype-1.10/</guid>
      <description>I originally intended vpype 1.10 to be a &amp;lsquo;quick-and-dirty&amp;rsquo;, bug-fix-only release but it ended up being quite substantial, so let&amp;rsquo;s dive in.
New features and improvements   Improved support for layer pen width and opacity in the viewer (#448)
 The &amp;ldquo;Pen Width&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Pen Opacity&amp;rdquo; menus are now named &amp;ldquo;Default Pen Width&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Default Pen Opacity&amp;rdquo;. The layer opacity is now used for display by default. It can be overridden by the default pen opacity by checking the &amp;ldquo;Override&amp;rdquo; item from the &amp;ldquo;Default Pen Opacity&amp;rdquo; menu.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TIL: aligning horizontal or vertical lines to the pixel grid with OpenGL</title>
      <link>https://bylr.info/articles/2022/04/05/til-aligning-horizontal-or-vertical-lines-to-the-pixel-grid-with-opengl/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bylr.info/articles/2022/04/05/til-aligning-horizontal-or-vertical-lines-to-the-pixel-grid-with-opengl/</guid>
      <description>When I started using my new M1 Max MacBook Pro in December, a bunch of vpype&amp;rsquo;s tests started to fail. The failing tests were all image-based: an image is rendered and then compared to a previously-generated, reference image. This process is made easy thanks to this Pytest fixture.
In this case, the reference images were generated long ago on my previous, Intel/AMD-based MacBook Pro. This GIF highlights the discrepancy I&amp;rsquo;d get with images generated on my new computer (notice how the ruler&amp;rsquo;s thickness varies):</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Annotated Release Notes: vpype 1.9</title>
      <link>https://bylr.info/articles/2022/03/03/annotated-release-notes-vpype-1.9/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bylr.info/articles/2022/03/03/annotated-release-notes-vpype-1.9/</guid>
      <description>vpype 1.9 is finally out! 🎉
I recently stumbled upon a post by Simon Willison where he promotes the idea of annotated release notes. As it turns out, this release is, by any metric I can think of, the biggest and most transformative so far. The associated change log is consequently rather unwieldy and calls, you guessed it 💡, for the present annotated release notes.
(Note: although the original release notes are extensively quoted in this article, I reshuffled and shortened the original material.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First post</title>
      <link>https://bylr.info/articles/2022/02/20/first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bylr.info/articles/2022/02/20/first-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello again, world.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://bylr.info/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2022 20:21:40 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bylr.info/about/</guid>
      <description>My name is Antoine Beyeler. I am a multi-disciplinary engineer and entrepreneur with a PhD in flying robotics and interests in software, aviation, photography, generative art, plotters, and home automation. I live in Lausanne, Switzerland 🇨🇭.
With a few friends, I co-founded senseFly in 2009, which soon became the leader of fixed-wing mapping drones for surveyors, farmers, humanitarians and many others. Until my departure in 2018, I lead as CTO a team of up to 45 engineers and developed multiple generations of end-to-end mapping drone systems.</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>
